<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//GNOME//DTD DocBook PNG Variant V1.0//EN"[
]>


 <article id="index">

  <artheader> 
    <title>The GNOME Panel</title>
    <copyright>
      <year>2000</year>
      <holder>Red Hat, Inc., Dan Mueth, and Alexander Kirillov</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        Permission is granted to make and distribute verbatim copies of this
        manual provided the copyright notice and this permission notice are
        preserved on all copies.
      </para>
      <para>
        Permission is granted to copy and distribute modified versions of
        this manual under the conditions for verbatim copying, provided that
        the entire resulting derived work is distributed under the terms of a
        permission notice identical to this one.
      </para>
      <para>
        Permission is granted to copy and distribute translations of this
        manual into another language, under the above conditions for modified
        versions, except that this permission notice may be stated in a
        translation approved by the Free Software Foundation.
      </para>

      <para> UNIX is a trademark of X/Open Group</para>
      <para> Linux is a trademark of Linus Torvalds </para>
      <para> X Window System is a trademark of X Consortium, Inc.</para>
      <para> Windows is a trademark of Microsoft Corp.</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <releaseinfo> 
		  This is version 1.0 of gnome-panel manual.
     </releaseinfo>
  </artheader> 
  <sect1>
   <title>Introduction</title>
   <para>
    <indexterm id="idx-a2">
     <primary>Panel</primary>
    </indexterm>
    The GNOME Panel is the heart of the GNOME user interface and acts
    as a repository for <link linkend="launchers">applications
    launchers</link>, <link linkend="applets">applets</link>
    (applications which run entirely within the panel), <link
    linkend="menus">menus</link>, <link
    linkend="drawers">drawers</link>, and several <link
    linkend="specialobjects">special objects</link>.  The Panel was
    designed to be highly configurable.  You can easily <link
    linkend="panelproperties">customize</link> its contents, behavior,
    and  appearance to suite your personal needs and preferences.  You
    can even have <link linkend="panelmove">multiple panels</link>,
    each with its own appearance, properties, and contents.  This
    flexibility allows you to easily create a comfortable and
    efficient personalized desktop environment.
   </para>
    <para> This manual describes version 1.1.4 of GNOME panel.
      </para>
  </sect1>


<!-- ########### Panel Basics  ############## --> 
  <sect1 id="panelbasic">  
   <title>Panel Basics</title>
   <para>
    Using the GNOME Panel is very simple and will come easily to
    anyone who has used a graphical desktop environment.  This section
    will give you a basic introduction to help you get started, and
    the following sections will discuss the various panel contents and
    features in more detail.
   </para>

   <sect2 id="intropanel">
    <title>Introduction to Panel Objects</title>
    <para>
     The Panel can hold several types of objects. The following
     example Panel shows each type of Panel object.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>An Example Panel</title>
     <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>An Example Panel.</screeninfo>
       <graphic fileref="./figures/example_panel" format="png"
       srccredit="muet">
       </graphic>
     </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <para>
     This example Panel contains the following objects:
     <itemizedlist>  
      <listitem> 
   
       <para>   <guilabel>Menus</guilabel> &mdash;
        <guilabel>Menus</guilabel> are lists of items, each of which
        either starts an application, executes a command, or is a
        sub-menu.  In the example Panel shown above, the left-most
        icon after the arrow is a stylized footprint icon(the GNOME
        logo). This is the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>, one of the
        most important objects in the Panel.  This menu provides
        access to almost all the applications, commands, and
        configuration options available in GNOME. The <guimenu>Main
        Menu</guimenu> is described in detail in <xref
        linkend="mainmenu">. The second icon shown is a folder, the
        default icon used for user <guilabel>Menus</guilabel>.  GNOME
        allows users to create their own <guilabel>Menus</guilabel>
        with personalized contents to use in addition to the
        <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>.  To open a
        <guimenu>Menu</guimenu>, just click on the icon with the left
        mouse button.  For more information on
        <guilabel>Menus</guilabel>, see <xref linkend="menus">.
       </para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>  

       <para> 
        <guilabel>Launchers</guilabel> &mdash; 
        <guilabel>Launchers</guilabel> are buttons which either start
        an application or execute a command when you press them(click
        with the left mouse button).
        The third and fourth icons in the example Panel are
        <guilabel>Launchers</guilabel> which start the
        <application>Gnumeric</application> and the <application>GNOME
        Calendar</application> applications. For more information on
        <guilabel>Launchers</guilabel>, see <xref linkend="launchers">. 
       </para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>  

       <para> 
        <guilabel>Applets</guilabel>  &mdash;
        <guilabel>Applets</guilabel> are applications which run inside
        a small part of the Panel. The fifth, sixth, and seventh icons
        in the example Panel above are all
        <guilabel>Applets</guilabel>. The first
        <guilabel>Applet</guilabel> shown is <application>GNOME
        Weather</application>, which periodically downloads the current
        weather conditions off the Web and displays the
        information. The second <guilabel>Applet</guilabel> is the
        <application>Drive Mount Applet</application>, which shows
        whether a disk (in this case, the floppy drive) is mounted and
        allows you to mount and unmount the drive with a single click
        of the mouse.  The third <guilabel>Applet</guilabel> shown is
        the <application>Quick Launch Applet</application>, which acts
        as a container for <guilabel>Launchers</guilabel>, but saves
        more space than placing your <guilabel>Launchers</guilabel>
        directly on the Panel.  For more information on
        <guilabel>Applets</guilabel>, see <xref linkend="applets">.
       </para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>    

       <para>  <guilabel>Drawers</guilabel> &mdash;
        <guilabel>Drawers</guilabel> are essentially extensions of the
        Panel which can be opened or closed.  They can hold anything
        the panel can.  The brown icon of a drawer in the example
        Panel above is the default icon for
        <guilabel>Drawers</guilabel>, although any icon can be
        used. Click on the <guilabel>Drawer</guilabel> with the left
        mouse button to open or close it.  For more information on
        <guilabel>Drawers</guilabel>, see <xref linkend="drawers">.
       </para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>    

       <para> 
        <guilabel>Special Objects</guilabel> &mdash;
        <guilabel>Special Objects</guilabel> are special items you can
        add to the Panel which perform commands which are generally
        not available through the other Panel objects. The last two
        items in the example Panel above are <guilabel>Special
        Objects</guilabel>. The first (the lock icon) is the <guibutton>Lock
        Screen</guibutton> button, which is used to lock the
        screen so other users cannot access it without knowing the
        password. The second is the <guibutton>Logout
        Button</guibutton> which begins the logout sequence to end
        your GNOME session. For more
        information on <guilabel>Special Objects</guilabel>, see <xref
        linkend="specialobjects">.
       </para>

      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </para>    
    <para>
     Each of these object types is described in detail in the following
     sections. You can easily add, move, or remove Panel objects
     &mdash; see <xref linkend="appletadd">.
    </para>
   </sect2>

 
   <sect2 id="rightclick">
    <title>Right-click menu</title>
    <para>
     Clicking on any panel object with the right mouse button brings
     up the <guimenu>pop-up</guimenu>  menu. This menu contains
     <guimenuitem>Remove from panel</guimenuitem> for removing the
     object from the panel, <guimenuitem>Move applet</guimenuitem> for
     moving objects within the Panel, the <guimenu>Panel</guimenu>
     menu described below, and object-specific items.  For Drawers,
     Menus, and Launchers the only object-specific item is
     a <guimenuitem>Properties...</guimenuitem> item which allows you
     to customize the properties and settings of the object. For Applets, the
     <guimenu>pop-up</guimenu> menu will often contain
     <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> for viewing information about
     the Applet such as the author's name and the Applet version,
     <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem> for viewing documentation about
     the Applet, and <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> for
     configuring preferences and settings for the Applet.  Applets
     often have other Applet-specific controls in the
     <guimenu>pop-up</guimenu> menu.
    </para>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu allows you to create and remove
     Panels and add objects to the Panel.  It also allows you to
     modify the properties of the particular Panel of interest using
     <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> (see <xref
     linkend="panelproperties">) or the properties of all panels using
     <guimenuitem>Global Preferences...</guimenuitem>(see <xref
     linkend="globalpanelprefs">).
    </para>
    <para>
     You can also right-click on the panel itself. This will
     bring up the <link linkend="mainmenu"><guimenu>Main
     Menu</guimenu></link>. In particular, this menu also contains the
     <guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu described above.
    </para>
   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="panelhide">
    <title>Hiding the Panel</title>
    <para>
     <indexterm id="idx-a4">
      <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>Hide Buttons</secondary>
     </indexterm>
     <indexterm id="idx-a5">
      <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>Hiding</secondary>
     </indexterm>
     The left and right arrow icons seen at either end of the example
     panel are used to hide the panel. These arrows are shown in the
     following figure.
     <figure>
      <title>The Hide Button</title>
      <screenshot>
       <screeninfo>The Hide Button</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="./figures/hide-button" format="png"
        srccredit="dcm">
        </graphic>
      </screenshot>
     </figure>
    </para>
    <para>
     Pressing one of these arrows will hide the GNOME Panel by sliding
     it in the direction of the arrow pressed.  Pressing it a second
     time will expand the Panel.
    </para>
    <para>
     The Panel can be configured to automatically hide when you are
     not using it and reappear when you move the mouse to the part of
     the screen where the Panel resides. This can be a helpful
     function if you are unable to run your system in a high
     resolution.  To learn how to have the Panel auto-hide, see <xref
     linkend="panelproperties">.
    </para>
   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="loggingout">
    <title>Logging Out</title>
    <para>
     To log out of GNOME, right click on either end of the Panel and
     select <guimenuitem>Log out</guimenuitem>. This will bring up the
     Logout Dialog seen below.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>The Logout Dialog</title>
     <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Logout</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="./figures/logout-screen" format="png"
      srccredit="dcm">
      </graphic>
     </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <para>
     If you would like to save your current setup, select the
     <guilabel>Save current setup</guilabel> checkbox. This will save
     any GNOME programs you have open and configuration changes you
     may have made in the Control Center.
    </para>
    <para>
     The default way of logging out is by using the
     <guilabel>Logout</guilabel> option, which ends your GNOME session
     but does not shut down the computer.  Depending on your system
     configuration, you may also have the <guilabel>Halt</guilabel>
     option, which shuts down the computer, and the
     <guilabel>Reboot</guilabel> option, which will reboot the
     computer.
    </para>
    <note>   <title>Note for advanced users</title>  <para>   The
     <guilabel>Halt</guilabel> and <guilabel>Reboot</guilabel> choices
     will only be shown if you have the permission to execute the
     command <command>/usr/bin/shutdown</command>.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     If you do not want to log out, press the
     <guibutton>No</guibutton> button and you will be returned to your
     GNOME session. Otherwise press the <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>
     button to log out.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Logging Out and Window Managers</title>
     <para>
      If you are running a window manager that is GNOME compliant, the
      logout feature will quit the window manager as well as GNOME. If
      you are running a non-compliant window manager you will have to
      quit the window manager yourself.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     You can disable the Logout Dialog so that pressing the logout
     button will end your GNOME session without asking any
     questions. To do so, start GNOME control center (<menuchoice>
     <guisubmenu>Startup programs</guisubmenu> </menuchoice>) and
     uncheck the button <guilabel>Prompt on logout</guilabel>. You may
     also control whether changes to your session are automatically
     saved using the <guilabel>Automatically save changes to
     session</guilabel> button.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="lockscreen">
    <title>Locking the Screen</title>
    <para>
     Sometimes you may want to leave your computer with GNOME running
     and not allow others to use or view your GNOME session.  GNOME
     allows you to do this by locking the screen, requiring a password
     to unlock it. To lock your GNOME session, right click on either
     end of a Panel and select <guimenuitem>Lock screen</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Screensavers and The Lock Button</title>
     <para>
      The <guibutton>Lock Button</guibutton> uses a feature of the
      <application>xscreensaver</application> program. This is the same
      program that the Control Center uses to set your screensaver. In
      order for the <guibutton>Lock Button</guibutton> to work
      properly, you must have a screensaver enabled in the Control
      Center.
     </para>
    </note>  
   </sect2>
  </sect1>



<!-- ########### Main Menu ############## -->

   <sect1 id="mainmenu">
    <title>The Main Menu</title>
    <para>
      <indexterm id="idx-a3">  <primary>Main Menu</primary>
     </indexterm>
      The footprint icon seen towards the left end of the example
      panel is the <guibutton>Main Menu</guibutton> (yes, you guessed
      right, it is the footprint of the gnome). This menu provides you
      access to almost all you can do with GNOME &mdash; all the
      applications, configuration tools, command line prompt,
      <guimenuitem>Logout</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Lock
      Screen</guimenuitem> commands, and much more.  To access any of
      its items, click on the <guibutton>Main Menu
      Button</guibutton>. You should release the mouse after pressing
      the <guibutton>Main Menu</guibutton> button so that you can take
      advantage of other mouse-activated features in the Main Menu
      such as right mouse clicks and drag and drop from the menu.
     <figure>
      <title>The Main Menu Button</title>
     <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>The Main Menu Button.</screeninfo>
       <graphic fileref="./figures/mm-button" format="png"
       srccredit="dcm">
       </graphic>
     </screenshot>
    </figure>
    </para>
   <sect2 id="submenus">
      <title> Components of the main menu</title>

      <para>
	The main component of the Main Menu is the
	<guimenu>Programs</guimenu> menu, which contains a list of
	preconfigured menu items. Here you will find all the GNOME
	applications, from <application>Gnumeric</application>
	spreadsheet to <application>Kanji terminal</application>, as
	well as quite a few non-Gnome ones, such as
	<application>Netscape</application> browser and
	<application>emacs</application> text editor.
	<guimenu>Programs</guimenu> menu also contains commands
	<guimenuitem>File manager</guimenuitem>, which launches the
	GNOME file manager, <guimenuitem>Run program</guimenuitem>,
	which gives you the command line prompt where you can enter
	any command, and <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>, which
	launches the GNOME help browser. GNOME help browser gives you
	an easy access to all the documentation installed on your
	system &mdash; not only GNOME documentation (Users guide,
	application manuals, &hellip;), but also all other types of
	documentation (man pages, info pages).
      </para>


      <para> In addition to the <guimenu>Programs</guimenu>,  the main
	menu can also contains a number of other submenus and useful
	commands, listed below. Depending on your configuration, you
	may not see all of them. Also, some of them may be shown as
	submenus, and others included as part of the main menu,
	separated by horizontal lines from other parts.
      </para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guisubmenu>Favorites.</guisubmenu> This menu, which is
	      originally empty, is the place where you can put your
	      favorite applications for quicker access. You can edit
	      this menu using the <application>Menu
	      Editor</application>, which can be accessed from the
	      <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> by choosing
	      <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Settings</guisubmenu>
	      <guimenuitem>Menu Editor</guimenuitem>
	      </menuchoice>. You can also add any item from any other
	      menu (in particular, from the
	      <guimenu>Programs</guimenu> menu) to
	      <guisubmenu>Favorites</guisubmenu> by clicking on the
	      item with the right mouse button and selecting
	      <guimenuitem>Add this to personal menu</guimenuitem>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guisubmenu>Applets.</guisubmenu> This menu contains all
	      the applets installed on your system.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>KDE menus.</guimenuitem> This  shows the
	      menus of the K Desktop Environment (KDE) if you have it
	      installed on your system
	    </para>
	  </listitem>


	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem> Another Level menus, Debian menus.
	      </guimenuitem> These menus show the default application
	      menus for Red Hat Linux (Another Level) and Debian
	      GNU/Linux. They only make sense for the users of
	      corresponding distributions.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem>Panel Menu.</guimenuitem> This menu can be
	    used to change panel properties (both for <link
	    linkend="panelproperties">this panel</link> and <link
	    linkend="globalpanelprefs">global</link>, i.e. for all
	    panels), <link linkend="add">add an object</link> to the
	    panel, remove the whole panel or <link
	    linkend="paneladd">create a new panel</link>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenuitem> Desktop menu</guimenuitem>&mdash; includes
	      <guimenuitem>Logout</guimenuitem>, which ends your GNOME
	      session (first asking for confirmation &mdash; see <xref
	      linkend="loggingout">) and <guimenuitem>Lock
	      Screen</guimenuitem>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem id="runcommand">
	  <para>
	    <guimenuitem> Run &hellip;</guimenuitem> &mdash; this
	    command gives you the command line prompt. It is not a
	    full-blown shell, so it is not a replacement for
	    <application>gnome-terminal</application>, but it is very
	    convenient when you need to enter just one command
	    quickly. You can also launch this command line prompt by
	    using a keyboard shortcut (you will need to specify the
	    key you want to use in the <link
	    linkend="misctab"><guilabel>Miscellaneous</guilabel></link>
	    tab of <interface><link linkend="globalpanelprefs">Global
	    Panel Preferences</link>  dialog</interface>).
	  </para>
	  <para>The command line prompt has history buffer (you can
	  recall any of previously entered command by pressing the down
	  arrow located to the right of the text field and selecting
	  this command) and
	  <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button, which allows you to
	  choose a file &mdash; the filename will be added at the end of
	  your command. For example, you can enter
	    <userinput>emacs</userinput> (an extremely powerful text
	  editor) on the command line and then use
	  <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button to 
	  select the file to be edited. 
	    </para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mainmenuconfig">
      <title>Configuring the main menu</title> 
      <para> To change configuration of the main menu, righ-click on
      it and select <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>  from the
      <guimenu>pop-up</guimenu> menu. This will show <interface>Menu
      Properties dialog</interface>. In this dialog, for each of
      the submenus  of the
      Main menu listed above (<guisubmenu>Programs</guisubmenu>,
      <guisubmenu>Favorites</guisubmenu>, &hellip;) you can choose
      whether you want it  to be shown as part of the main menu, as a
      submenu, or not shown at all.
      </para>

   <figure>
   <title>Menu Properties Dialog</title>
   <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Menu Properties Dialog</screeninfo>
     <graphic fileref="./figures/menu_properties" format="png"
     srccredit="muet">
     </graphic>
    </screenshot>
   </figure>

      <para>
	You can also edit the contents of the
	<guisubmenu>Favorites</guisubmenu> menu (or, if you are the
	system administartor, also of the
	<guisubmenu>Programs</guisubmenu> menu) using the
	<application>GNOME Menu Editor</application>. To start it,
	right-click on the main menu button and select
	<guimenuitem>Edit Menus</guimenuitem>. Alternatively, you can
	start <application>GNOME Menu Editor</application> by
	selecting 
	<menuchoice> <guisubmenu>Programs</guisubmenu>
	  <guisubmenu>Settings</guisubmenu>
	  <guimenuitem>Menu Editor</guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice> from the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> itself. 
      </para>
    </sect2>

  <sect2 id="kbdnav">
   <title>Keyboard navigation in the main menu</title> <para> If you
      prefer, you can use keyboard instead of the mouse to navigate
      the main menu. To activate the main menu, press
      <keycap>Menu</keycap> key on your keyboard (if you are using
      standard PC keyboard, this key usually is located to the left of
      the space bar and labelled with a picture of a menu); you can
      change the default key in the <link
      linkend="misctab"><guilabel>Miscellaneous</guilabel></link> tab
      of <interface><link linkend="globalpanelprefs">Global Panel
      Preferences</link> dialog</interface>. After this, you can use
      <keycap>Up</keycap> and <keycap>Down</keycap> arrows to move
      inside the menu, <keycap>Right</keycap> arrow to go to a
      submenu, and <keycap>Enter</keycap> to select an item. To hide
      the menu again, just press <keycap>Esc</keycap>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>




<!-- ########### Menus  ############## -->
 <sect1 id="menus">
  <title>Menus</title>
  <para>
      In addition to the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>, discussed in
      <xref linkend="mainmenu">, you can also add to the Panel "normal
      menus". Unlike the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>, normal Menus
      only contain whatever Launchers and submenus you choose put in
      them - no default submenus, Run program, etc. as the
      <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> has.  For example, you can add any
      submenu of your <guimenu>Favorites</guimenu> menu or the
      <guimenu>Program</guimenu> menu as a separate menu to the panel;
      to do so, bring up this submenu from the Main Menu, right click
      on the submenu title, and select <guimenuitem>add this menu to
      panel</guimenuitem>.  To create a new Menu, use the
      <application>Menu editor</application>.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>An Example Menu</title>
   <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>An Example Menu</screeninfo>
     <graphic fileref="./figures/example_menu" format="png"
     srccredit="muet">
     </graphic>
   </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <para>
   The example above shows a menu titled "My Favorites" which includes
   three application launchers and one sub-menu titled "games".
  </para>
   <sect2 id="menusconf">
    <title> Configuring the menus</title>
     <para> 
      To learn how you can add new menus to the Panel, see <xref
      linkend="add">.  
     </para>
     <para> You can easily change the Menu title and the icon used by the
      Menu. To do so, click on the Menu button, right-click on the
      menu title (at the very top of the list, above all other items),
      and select <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem> from the
      <guimenu>pop-up</guimenu> menu. This will bring up the Menu
      Properties Dialog, quite
      similar to the <link linkend="launchers">Launcher
      Properties Dialog</link>.  
     </para> 
     <para> To add a new item to the
      Menu, click on the Menu button, right-click on the Menu title,
      and select <guimenuitem>Add new item to this
      menu</guimenuitem>. FIXME To remove an item from the Menu,
      righ-click on it and choose <guimenuitem>Remove this
      item</guimenuitem>.  
      </para>
      <para>
	Finally, a frequently asked question is "How I can change the
	font and the background used by the menus?" The answer is, it
	is determined by the current GTK Theme, which can be changed
	using <application>GNOME Control Center</application>, by
	selecting <menuchoice> <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>
	  <guisubmenu>Settings</guisubmenu> 
          <guisubmenu>Desktop</guisubmenu> 
	  <guimenuitem>Theme Selector</guimenuitem>
	</menuchoice>.
	</para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>


<!-- ###########  Launchers  ############## -->
 <sect1 id="launchers">
  <title>Launchers</title>
  <para>
   Launchers are essentially buttons which reside in your panel and
   start an application or execute a command when clicked.  A launcher
   can use any icon and has a customized tooltip to display a message
   when the cursor is passed over the Launcher.
  </para>
  <figure id="launcherpropsfig">
   <title>Create Launcher/Launcher Properties Dialog</title>
   <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Create Launcher/Launcher Properties Dialog</screeninfo>
     <graphic fileref="./figures/create_launcher" format="png"
     srccredit="muet">
     </graphic>
   </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <figure id="launcheradvpropsfig">
   <title>Launcher Advanced Properties Dialog</title>
   <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Launcher Advanced Properties Dialog</screeninfo>
     <graphic fileref="./figures/launcher_advprops" format="png"
     srccredit="muet">
     </graphic>
   </screenshot>
  </figure>
 </sect1>


<!-- ###########  Applets  ############## -->
 <sect1 id="applets">
  <title>Applets</title>
  <para>
   Applets are GNOME applications which reside in the Panel. An
   Applet's appearance typically reveals the state of the Applet or
   other information. Applets often have buttons, sliders, entries, or
   other methods to allow you to control their behavior.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Example Applets</title>
   <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Example Applets</screeninfo>
     <graphic fileref="./figures/panel_applets" format="png"
     srccredit="muet">
     </graphic>
   </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <para>
   Some example Applets are shown above.  At the very left is  the
   <application>Sound Monitor Applet</application>, which displays
   the current volume of sound being played and allows us to control
   various sound features.  Second is the <application>Mixer
   Applet</application>, which allows us to turn on/off sound and
   control its volume by clicking on applet.  This is followed by the
   <application>Battery Power Applet</application>, useful for
   monitoring the battery on a laptop. The fourth applet is the
   <application>GTCD Applet</application>, a CD player which has all
   its controls available in the applet and displays the track and
   time. The next applet is the <application>Drive Mount
   Applet</application>, used to mount and unmount drives with a
   single click of the mouse. The last applet shown is an analog
   clock, displaying the current time.
  </para>
  <para>
   GNOME has many useful applets.  Just right click on your Panel and
   add some applets to your panel to find out what is available and
   which ones are best for you.
  </para>
 </sect1>


<!-- ###########  Drawers  ############## -->
 <sect1 id="drawers">
  <title>Drawers</title>
  <para>
   The simplest way of thinking about a Drawer is that it is a
   container to store things.  Typically one may use a Drawer to hold
   multiple launchers which are related to each other in some way,
   such as the various applications in GNOME Office. The Drawers in
   the GNOME Panel take this one step further by making a Drawer an
   actual extension of the Panel itself.  Thus, a Drawer is a
   collapsible branch of an existing Panel.  It can contain anything
   that a Panel can, including Launchers, Applets, and other Drawers.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>An open Drawer</title>
   <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>An open Drawer</screeninfo>
    <graphic fileref="./figures/drawer_open" format="png"
    srccredit="dcm">
    </graphic>
   </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <para>
   Once you have placed a Drawer on the Panel, you may click on it to
   "open" the Drawer, revealing its contents.   You may then add items
   to the Drawer in the same way you would add items to the panel,
   right clicking on the end of the drawer with the arrow.  You can
   close the Drawer by clicking on its icon again or by clicking on
   the arrow at its end.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can configure a Drawer's properties by right clicking on the
   Drawer's icon and selecting
   <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>. This brings up the Drawer
   Properties Dialog. Here you can select the icon used for the drawer
   by clicking on the icon. A tooltip may be entered by typing in the
   <guilabel>Tooltip/Name</guilabel> entry. This tooltip will be
   displayed whenever the mouse is moved over the Drawer to remind you
   what is inside.  One may also select whether the <guibutton>hide
   button</guibutton> and arrow are displayed at the end of the drawer.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Drawer Properties Dialog</title>
   <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Drawer Properties Dialog</screeninfo>
    <graphic fileref="./figures/drawer_properties" format="png"
     srccredit="dcm">
    </graphic>
   </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <para>
   You may also control the background of the Drawer. Just right click
   on the Drawer and select the "Background" tab to bring up the
   standard Panel Background Dialog (see <xref
   linkend="panelbacktab">).  </para>
 </sect1>



<!-- ###########  Special Panel Objects  ############## -->
 <sect1 id="specialobjects">
  <title>Special Panel Objects</title>
  <para>
   There are several special panel objects which are not considered
   Menus, Applets, or Launchers.  These special objects are described
   below.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="lockbutton">
   <title>The Lock Button</title>
   <figure>
    <title>The Lock Button</title>
    <screenshot>
     <screeninfo>The Lock Button</screeninfo>
     <graphic fileref="./figures/panel_lockbut" format="png"
     srccredit="muet">
     </graphic>
    </screenshot>
   </figure>
   <para>
    The <guibutton>Lock Button</guibutton> is a Panel button which
    begins a screensaver which locks the screen. In order to remove
    the screensaver and access the GNOME session again, you must
    supply your password.  This is typically used when you must leave
    your computer for a while and do not want to log out or allow
    other people to use your computer. To lock your screen, simply
    click on the <guibutton>Lock Button</guibutton>.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Screensavers and The Lock Button</title>
    <para>
     The <guibutton>Lock Button</guibutton> uses a feature of the
     <application>xscreensaver</application> program. This is the same
     program that the Control Center uses to set your screensaver. In
     order for the <guibutton>Lock Button</guibutton> to work
     properly, you must have a screensaver enabled in the Control
     Center.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="logoutbutton">
   <title>The Logout Button</title>
   <figure id="logoutbuttonfig">
    <title>The Logout Button</title>
    <screenshot>
     <screeninfo>The Logout Button</screeninfo>
     <graphic fileref="./figures/panel_logoutbut"
     format="png" srccredit="muet">
     </graphic>
    </screenshot>
   </figure>
   <para>
    The <guibutton>Logout</guibutton> button is used to exit the GNOME
    desktop environment.  It initiates the logout sequence, bringing
    up the Logout Dialog, as described in <xref linkend="loggingout">.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="swallowedapps">
   <title>Swallowed Applications</title>
   <para>
    The GNOME Panel allows you to run applications which are not
    Applets inside the Panel as if they were Applets.  Applications
    which you pull into the Panel, even though they are not GNOME
    Applets are called "swallowed applications".  Applications do not
    have to be GNOME-compliant to be swallowed.  In general, the only
    constraints for swallowing an application are that the application
    must be small enough to fit in your panel and you must know the
    title of the window you would like to swallow.  In many cases, the
    application can be automatically shrank to fit in the Panel, as
    specified in the Create Swallowed Application Dialog.
   </para>
   <figure id="swallappfig">
     <title>Create Swallowed Application Dialog</title>
     <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Create Swallowed Application Dialog</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="./figures/panel_swallow" format="png"
      srccredit="muet">
      </graphic>
     </screenshot>
    </figure>
   <para>
    The "Title of application to swallow" is the window title,
    typically displayed on the top left edge of the window. (Note that
    the window title is case sensitive.) The width
    and height determine the size of the swallowed application in the
    panel in pixels.  The
    optional "Command" entry is used to execute a command before
    swallowing the application.  This can be used to start an
    application which you want the Panel to swallow.
   </para>
         
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="statusdock">
   <title>Status Dock</title>
   <para>
    The Status Dock is a Panel object which can hold Status Docklets -
    small windows which applications place in the Status Dock to
    provide status information.  Status Docklets can also be used to
    control the application.  GNOME currently does not have many
    applications which place Status Docklets in the Status Dock.
    However, GNOME's Status Dock is compatible with that on KDE, so
    KDE applications (eg: kscd) may place Status Docklets in GNOME's
    Status Dock.  Future versions of GNOME applications will make use
    of this recently added Panel object.
   </para>
   <figure id="statusdockfig">
     <title>Example Status Dock With Docklet</title>
     <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Example Status Dock With Docklet</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="./figures/status_dock" format="png"
      srccredit="lebl">
      </graphic>
     </screenshot>
    </figure>
   <para>
    The above example shows the Status Dock with a Status Docklet from the
    <application>kscd</application> CD player program.  This
    particular Docklet is used to open and close the main
    <application>kscd</application> window without ending the program.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>


<!-- ########### Adding, Moving, and Removing Panel Objects
############## -->
    <sect1 id="appletadd">
      <title>Adding, Moving, and Removing Panel Objects</title>
      <sect2 id="moving">
	<title>Moving objects</title>
	<para>
<!--
     <indexterm id="idx-a14">
      <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>launchers</secondary>
     </indexterm>
     <indexterm id="idx-a15">
      <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>adding applets
      to</secondary><see>"Applets"</see> </indexterm> --> 

	To move any
      object on the panel to a different location, just drag it with
      the middle mouse button to the desired place, or right-click on
      it and choose <guimenuitem>Move applet</guimenuitem>. If in the
      course of this movement it hits other objects, the behaviour
      depends on the global preferences you set (see <xref
      linkend="appletstab">): the object you are moving can
      switch places with other objects, "push" all objects it meets,
      or "jump" over all other objects without disturbing them. You
      can also overrun the default behaviour by holding
      <keycap>Shift</keycap> button (for "push" mode), 
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> (for "switched" mode), or
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> (for "free" mode, i.e. jumping other other
      objects without disturbing them) button while
      dragging.
	</para>
      </sect2>
	<sect2 id="remove">
	  <title> Removing objects from the panel</title> <para>  To
	  remove an object from the panel, right-click on it and
	  choose <guimenuitem>Remove from panel</guimenuitem> form the
	  pop-up menu.
	    </para>
	</sect2>


    <sect2 id="add">  <title>Adding objects to the panel</title>

      <para>
	<indexterm id="idx-a13">
	  <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>adding applications
	  to</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	By default, the GNOME panel contains very few basic objects,
	such as the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>. However, there is a
	number of things you can add to it. For example, every menu
	item in the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> or its submenus can
	be added to the panel as an application launcher. GNOME also
	contains a number of applets that can be added to the panel,
	ranging from <application>Printer Applet</application>, which
	prints a file which you drag and drop onto this applet, to
	<application>Wanda the Fish</application>. If these are not
	enough, there is also a number of GNOME applets available on
	the Internet.
      </para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term> <emphasis>Applets</emphasis></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		To add an applet, right-click on the panel and select
		<menuchoice><guisubmenu>Add to panel</guisubmenu>
		<guisubmenu>Applet</guisubmenu></menuchoice> from the
		<guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu. This will show you the
		menu of all the applets on your system, divided into
		categories; choosing any applet from this menu will
		add it to the panel.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	  <varlistentry>
	    <term> <emphasis>Application launchers</emphasis></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		To create a new application launcher, select
		<menuchoice><guisubmenu>Add to panel</guisubmenu>
		<guimenuitem>Launcher</guimenuitem> </menuchoice> from
		the <guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu.  You will be
		presented the <interface>Create Launcher
		dialog</interface>, shown below.  In this dialog you
		should enter a name for your launcher, a comment, and
		the command line to launch the application.  You may
		also press the icon button and choose an icon to
		represent the application from the icon picker. If no
		icon is chosen a default icon will be used.  This
		dialog has a built-in help which explains its usage in
		detail.
	      </para>
	      <figure>
		<title>The Create Launcher Dialog</title>
		<screenshot>
		  <screeninfo>Create launcher dialog</screeninfo>
		  <graphic fileref="./figures/create_launcher" format="png"
			   srccredit="muet">
		  </graphic>
		</screenshot>
	      </figure>
	      <para>
		You can also add to the panel any existing menu item
		or any launcher on your desktop: just drag it to the
		panel and drop there. Be careful to drop in the empty
		space on the panel and not on any existing object: for
		example, if you drop it on the printer applet, it will
		be printed. For menu items, you can also right-click
		on an item in the menu and select <guimenuitem>Add
		this launcher to the panel</guimenuitem>. After this,
		you can change any options for that launcher by
		clicking on it with the right mouse button and
		selecting <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> menu
		item.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term> <emphasis>Menus</emphasis></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>To add a menu, select <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Add
		to panel</guisubmenu> <guisubmenu>Menu</guisubmenu>
		</menuchoice>  from the <guimenu>Panel</guimenu>
		menu. This gives you a choice of the <guimenu>Main
		menu</guimenu>, <guimenu>Programs</guimenu> menu, and
		<guimenu>Favorites</guimenu> menu.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		You can also add the <guimenu>Main menu</guimenu> or
		any its submenu  as a new menu to the panel by
		right-clicking  on the menu title (the top line of the
		menu, separated from menu items by a thin line) and
		selecting <guimenuitem>Add this as a menu to the
		panel</guimenuitem>.
	      </para>
	    <para> Advanced users can also create new menus
	      manually. To do so, you need to know that internally,
	      GNOME represents a menu by a directory, with menu items
	      presented by files of special type
	      (<filename>.desktop</filename> files &mdash; these files
	      also represent the application launchers), and submenus
	      presented by directories. For example, the
	      <guimenu>Favorites</guimenu> menu corresponds to the
	      directory <filename>~/.gnome/apps</filename> (where
	      <filename>~</filename> denotes your home directory), and
	      the <guimenu>Programs</guimenu> menu corresponds to the
	      directory
	      <filename>/usr/share/gnome/apps</filename>. Thus, you
	      can create a new directory, using the GNOME File
	      Manager, drag and drop there any
	      <filename>.desktop</filename> files from any other
	      directories you might have (for example, from
	      <filename>/usr/share/gnome/apps</filename>) or from the
	      desktop, and then drag and drop this directory from the
	      File Manager window to the panel. This will add this
	      directory as a menu to the panel.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      After you have added a menu to the panel using any of
	      the methods describee above, you can modify its
	      properties (for example, add new items to this menu or
	      change the icon used by the menu), as decribed in <xref
	      linkend="menus">.
	    </para>

	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term> <emphasis>Drawers</emphasis></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
                 To add a new empty drawer, select
		<menuchoice><guisubmenu>Add to panel</guisubmenu>
		<guisubmenu>Drawer</guisubmenu> </menuchoice> from the
		<guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu. After this, you can
		right-click on this drawer and select
		<guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> to change its
		properties (for example, the icon it uses). You can
		add new items to this drawer in the same way as you
		add items to the panel: all the methods for adding new
		objects to the panel described in this section will
		also work for adding new items to the drawer.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      You can also add the <guimenu>Main menu</guimenu> or any
		its submenu as a new drawer to the panel by
		right-clicking on the menu title and selecting
		<guimenuitem>Add this as a drawer to the
		panel</guimenuitem>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term> <emphasis>Swallowed application</emphasis></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>To add a new swallowed application, select
		<menuchoice><guisubmenu>Add to panel</guisubmenu>
		<guisubmenu>Swallowed app</guisubmenu> </menuchoice>
		from the <guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu. This will
		produce a <interface>Create Swallowed
		Application</interface> dialog, which is shown in
		<xref linkend="swallappfig">. For details, see <xref
		linkend="swallowedapps">. FIXME
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

   </sect2>
 </sect1>




<!-- ########### Creating, Moving, and Removing Panels  ##############
-->
  <sect1 id="panelmove">
   <title>Creating, Moving, and Removing Panels</title>

      <sect2 id="panelmoving">
	<title> Moving panels </title> <para>
	<indexterm id="idx-a7">
	  <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>moving</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	  Any Panel you have on your desktop can be moved by using the
	  middle mouse button, or by simultaneously pressing the left
	  and right mouse buttons, to drag the panel to the desired
	  edge of your screen. If you do not have a middle mouse
	  button and did not configure your mouse to emulate a middle
	  button you may also move a Panel by changing its location in
	  the <interface>Panel properties</interface> dialog.  You can
	  read more about this in <xref linkend="panelproperties"> of
	  this documentation.
	</para>
      </sect2>
    <sect2 id="panelremoving">
      <title> Removing panels </title> 
      <para>
	To remove an existing panel, right-click on it and choose 
	<guimenuitem>Remove this panel</guimenuitem> command from
	the  <guisubmenu>Panel</guisubmenu> menu. You
	will be prompted for a confirmation. 
      </para>
      <note> 
	<title>NOTE</title>
	<para>
	  At all times, you must have at least one panel; GNOME will
	  not allow you to remove your only panel.
	</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
      <sect2 id="paneladd">  <title>Creating new panels</title>
	  <para>
	<indexterm id="idx-a8">
	  <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>adding new</secondary>
	</indexterm>
	To add a new Panel to your desktop, select the
	<guimenuitem>Create panel</guimenuitem> command from
	<guisubmenu>Panel</guisubmenu> menu. You have a
	choice of four possible panel types:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <indexterm id="idx-a9">
	      <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>Edge</secondary>
	    </indexterm>
	    <guilabel>Edge Panel</guilabel> &mdash; An Edge Panel is
	    exactly like the main Panel that starts up with GNOME; it
	    stretches along the whole length of one of screen
	    edges. By selecting this type of panel you may add a new
	    Panel to another edge of your screen to give yourself more
	    functionality.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guilabel>Aligned Panel</guilabel> &mdash;  Aligned Panel
	     is also positioned along one of the screen edges. But
	     unlike the Edge Panel, the Aligned Panel will not stretch
	     across the entire edge of the screen it is on: it will
	     only stretch as much as necessary to  display the icons
	     and applets it contains. It can be positioned either at
	     one of the corners (in this case, it will stretch towards
	     the opposite corner) or at the center of the edge (in
	     this case, it will stretch in both directions,
	     automatically recentering when you add new objects).
            </para>
	  <para> If the Aligned panel is aligned with one of the
	    corners, the hide buttons will work slightly differently
	    than for the Edge Panel.  The hide button closest to the
	    edge of your screen will hide the Panel as usual but the
	    other hide button will send the whole panel to the
	    opposite edge. When the latter move is made it will not
	    hide the Panel since it is changing the side of the screen
	    it resides on.  If you want to hide it you will have to
	    press the hide button once again.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <guilabel>Sliding Panel</guilabel> &mdash; This type
 	        of panel is very similar to the Aligned Panel, but can
 	        be placed anywhere along the screen edge, not
 	        necessarily in one of the corners or in the center. As
 	        you add objects, it will only grow in one directions
 	        &mdash; it won't automatically recenter.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<guilabel> Floating  Panel</guilabel> &mdash;   This
		type of panel can be placed anywhere on your screen,
		not necessarily along one of the edges.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	<tip>
	  <title> Changing panel type</title>
	  <para>
	      <indexterm id="idx-a11">
	      <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>changing type
	      of</secondary>
	    </indexterm>
	  You can also change type of existing panel &mdash; for
	  example, convert edge panel to a floating panel, see <xref
	  linkend="panelproperties">.
	  </para>
	</tip>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>


<!-- ############### Global Panel Preferences  ################## -->
  <sect1 id="globalpanelprefs">
   <title>Global Panel Preferences</title>
    <para>
      <indexterm id="idx-a61"> 
	<primary>Panel</primary>
	<secondary>Global Panel Preferences</secondary> 
      </indexterm>
     To start configuring the GNOME panel, select <guimenuitem>Global
     Preferences</guimenuitem> from the <guisubmenu>Panel</guisubmenu>
     submenu of the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> (you can access
     the main menu by either pressing the foot icon or by
     right-clicking on the panel).  
    </para>
    <para>
     This will bring the <interface>Global Panel
     Preferences</interface>  dialog up  (this dialog is one of the
     components of the GNOME Control Center).  With
     this dialog you can set properties that will affect all Panels
     you use now and any panels you add in the future.
     <figure>
      <title>The Global Panel Configuration Dialog</title>
     <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>The Global Panel Configuration Dialog</screeninfo>
       <graphic fileref="./figures/glob_pref_anim"
       format="png" srccredit="muet">
       </graphic>
     </screenshot>
     </figure>
    </para>
    <para>
     The Global Panel Configuration Dialog contains five tabs which
     help you configure the global properties of the GNOME Panel:
     <guilabel>Animation</guilabel>, <guilabel>Buttons</guilabel>,
     <guilabel>Applets</guilabel>, <guilabel>Menu</guilabel>, and 
     <guilabel>Miscellaneous</guilabel>. Each of these tabs is explained below.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="animtab">
     <title>Animation  Tab</title>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Enable animations</guilabel> &mdash; This allows the
       animations configurable on this tab to be visible.  The
       animations must be enabled to use the other features of this
       tab. The default position is on.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Constant speed animations</guilabel> &mdash; By
       default, the animations start slowly, but then accelerate. If
       you enable this option, the animations will not use any
       acceleration.   
      </para>
     </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Auto hide animation speed</guilabel> &mdash; If you have
       the panel hiding automatically this will control how fast it
       occurs.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Explicit hide animation speed</guilabel> &mdash;  This
       controls the hide speed when you press the Panel's Hide Button.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Drawer sliding animation speed</guilabel> &mdash; this
       will control how fast the drawer menu will raise when you press
       a Drawer button on the Panel. 
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Auto hide delay (ms)</guilabel> &mdash; If you have
       the Panel set to minimize automatically this will allow you to
       control how much time passes before it minimizes.  The Panel
       will start the time count once the mouse is no longer over
       it. It will appear again when the mouse is passed over the
       portion of the Panel that remains visible. This time is
       measured in milliseconds.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Auto hide minimized size (pixels)</guilabel> &mdash; If you
       have the Panel hiding automatically this determines the number
       of pixels that will show while the Panel is minimized.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="launchtab">
    <title>Buttons Tab</title>
      <para> In this section, you can set appearance of buttons of
      various types (launcher buttons, menu buttons, drawer buttons,
      and special (Logout and Lock Screen) buttons). 
      </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Tiles enabled</guilabel> &mdash; This checkbox will enable
       background tiles for buttons of given type on the Panel. 
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Normal Tile</guilabel> &mdash; This shows the image
       used for the tile in the up position (inactive, not
       pressed). To choose another image file, just click on the
       image, and it will launch the icon browser. Tiles must be
       enabled to access this option.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Clicked Tile</guilabel> &mdash; This shows the image
       used for the tile in the down position (active, pressed). To
       choose another image file, just press on the image, and it will
       launch the icon browser. Tiles must be enabled to access this
       option.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Border width (tile only)</guilabel> &mdash; This
       determines the width of the border around an icon. For example,
       if you set border width equal to 5, this will ensure that at
       least 5 pixels of the tile will be shown on every side of the
       icon; if necessary, the icon will be cropped. This is very
       useful if you have an icon that would normally cover up a tile.
       Tiles must be enabled to access this option.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Depth (displacement when pressed)</guilabel> &mdash;
       This determines the depth an icon will displace when
       pressed. Tiles must be enabled to access this option.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
      <para> This tab also contains 3 options which affect all types
      of buttons simultaneously:
     </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem> 
	  <para> <guilabel>Make buttons flush with panel
	  edge</guilabel> &mdash; FIXME
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><guilabel>Show button tiles only when cursor is over
	  the button</guilabel> &mdash; if this option is enabled, the
	  tiles will only appear when mouse cursor is over the
	  butotn. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guilabel> Keep saturation low when cursor is not over the
	    button</guilabel> &mdash; Choosing this option will dim
	    the panel buttons; the button will brighten up when the
	    mouse cursor is over it.  
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
    <sect2 id="appletstab">
      <title>Applets Tab</title>
      <para>
	This tab shows some options related to placement and moving
	objects on the panel (contrary to the title, this options
	apply not only to applets but to all objects &mdash; applets,
	application launchers, menus, etc.). 
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guilabel> Default movement mode </guilabel> &mdash; here
	    you can choose the default mode for moving the objects on
	    the panel. Possible variants are
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para>
		  <emphasis>Switched</emphasis> &mdash; when the object you are
	    moving hits another object, they switch places
		  </para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para> 
		  <emphasis>Free</emphasis> &mdash; when the object
		  you are moving hits another object, it "jumps" over
		  it, so no other object is disturbed &mdash; this is
		  a convenient option if you like the current
		  arrangement of objects on your panel and want to
		  lock it
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>Push</emphasis> &mdash; the object you are
		  moving pushes all other objects in front of it, like a
		  snowplow.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  <para>You can override the default movement
	    mode by dragging an  object while holding
	    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> (for switched movement),
	    <keycap>Alt</keycap> (for free movement), or
	    <keycap>Shift</keycap> (for push movement) button pressed.
	    </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guilabel>Applet padding</guilabel> &mdash;  This changes
	    the amount of space (padding) between objects on the
	    panel. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

   <sect2 id="menutab">
    <title>Menu  Tab</title>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Use Large Icons</guilabel> &mdash; This will use large
       icons (rather than the default size) in menus. Only practical
       for those with high resolution screens (1280x1024 and higher)
      </para>
     </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Show ... buttons</guilabel> &mdash; This will enable three
       small dots to appear on Main Menu items that launch dialogs.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Show popup menus outside of panels</guilabel> &mdash; When
       this button is on, it allows popup menus to appear away from the
       Panel. When toggled off, the popups will appear over the
       Panel. This can be useful on smaller screens or cluttered
       desktops.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Keep menus in memory</guilabel> &mdash; This will keep your
       menus in memory so that they do not rescan for added
       items. This can increase the speed of GNOME, but may also
       result in you missing new items added to your menu.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem> 
	  <para> <guilabel>Panel Menu</guilabel> &mdash; FIXME
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>


   <sect2 id="misctab">
    <title>Miscellaneous Tab</title>
     <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Tooltips enabled</guilabel> &mdash; This enables tooltips
       for items on the panel.  Tooltips are pop-up help dialogs that
       appear when you mouse is over an element on the panel.
      </para>
	</listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Close drawer if a launcher inside it is
       pressed</guilabel> &mdash; By default drawers will remain open when
       you select an item within one. This can be annoying as the
       drawer will remain open until you close it with a mouse
       click. With this option selected drawers will close
       automatically when you select any item within one.
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Raise panels on mouse-over</guilabel> - If you are
       using a window manager that is not GNOME compliant it will not
       understand its relationship with the Panel. This can cause your
       Panel to be covered by applications. If you enable this feature
       you can have the Panel automatically raise when your mouse is
       over it.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Keep panel below windows</guilabel> &mdash; If you are
       using a GNOME compliant window manager the window manager will
       understand its relationship with the Panel. If you choose this
       feature the window manager and GNOME will allow applications to
       appear over the Panel. This can be useful on smaller screens.
      </para>
     </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guilabel>Confirm removal of panels with a
	      dialog</guilabel> &mdash; If this option is enabled,
	      GNOME will ask for confirmation before removing a
	      panel. 
	      </para>
	  </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
      <para>
      This tab also allows you to configure some global key
      bindings. At the moment, you can define keybindings for Main
      Menu and for Run Command dialog. For example, if you are using
      satndard PC keyboard, you can bind the <keycap>Menu</keycap> key
      (this key is usually  located to the left of the space bar and
      labelled with a picture of a menu) to the Main Menu, so that
      pressing this key will bring up the Main Menu. To change the key
      bound to Main Menu or to the Run Dialog, you can either select a
      key from the drop-down list, or click on the
      <guibutton>Grab</guibutton> button and then press the desired
      key. </para>
   </sect2>
   </sect1>


<!-- ###############  Individual Panel Properties  ################ -->

   <sect1 id="panelproperties">
    <title>Individual Panel Properties</title>
    <para>
     <indexterm id="idx-a62"> <primary>Panel</primary>
      <secondary>Individual Panel Properties</secondary>
     </indexterm>
     <indexterm id="idx-a63">
      <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>properties</secondary>
      </indexterm> 

      In addition to global Panel's properties, described in <xref
      linkend="globalpanelprefs">, some properties can be configured
      individually for each panel.  This includes panel type (Edge,
      Aligned, Sliding, Floating), size, location, background color,
      and hiding preferences. To change these properties for a panel,
      click on it with the right mouse button and select
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Panel</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Properties</guisubmenu></menuchoice>. You may also
      press the <guibutton>Main Menu</guibutton> button and select
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Panel</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Properties</guisubmenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para> From the <guisubmenu>Properties</guisubmenu>, you can
      choose <guimenuitem>All properties</guimenuitem>, which will
      launch <interface>Panel properties</interface> dialog.  If you
      are already familiar with this dialog, you can also quickly
      change some of the properties &mdash; say, panel size or type
      &mdash; by selecting the appropriate item  in the
      <guisubmenu>Properties</guisubmenu> menu.
    </para>
    <para>
     The Panel properties dialog contains two tabs to help you set the
     active Panel properties: <guilabel>Edge Panel</guilabel> (or
     <guilabel>Aligned</guilabel>, &hellip - depending on your panel
     type) and <guilabel>Background</guilabel>. Both of these tabs are
     explained below.
    </para>

   <sect2 id="edgetab">
    <title>Edge Panel Tab</title>
    <figure>
     <title>Panel Edge Properties Dialog</title>
    <screenshot>
     <screeninfo>Panel Edge Properties Dialog</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="./figures/panel_props_edge"
      format="png" srccredit="muet">
      </graphic>
    </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <guilabel>Panel Position</guilabel> &mdash; This changes
	    the position of the Panel on the screen. For edge panel,
	    you must specify an edge  (Top, Right, Left or
	    Bottom). For Aligned panel, you have to specify an edge
	    and one of the edge's ends or the center. For Sliding
	    Panel, you must specify the edge and offset from one of
	    the corners (in pixels). Finally, for Floating panel you
	    must specify orientation (horizontal or vertical) and
	    position of panel's left top corner (relative to the left
	    top corner of the screen and measured in pixels).
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    The Panel will change position once you have pressed
	    <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> or <guibutton>OK</guibutton>
	    buttons.
	  </para>
	  <tip>
	    <title>TIP</title>
	    <para>
	      You can also change Panel position by dragging it with
	      the middle mouse button to the new location.
	      </para>
	  </tip>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><guilabel>Panel size</guilabel> &mdash; here you can
	  choose panel width. The default size is 48 pixels, which is
	  also the default size of icons used by GNOME. Users with low
	  screen resolution might want to decrease the panel size to
	  free some screen space; conversely, users with high
	  resolution displays may try using larger panel sizes.
	    </para>
	    <para>
             Changing panel size automatically resizes all the icons
             on this panel, which can lead to some quality loss.
	  </para>
	</listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
 <!-- <indexterm id="idx-a64"> <primary>Panel</primary>
       <secondary>Auto-hide</secondary> </indexterm> -->

	    <guilabel>Hiding</guilabel> &mdash; In this section, you
	    can choose whether you want to enable panel Auto Hide
	    &mdash; that is, have the panel automatically hide when
	    the mouse is not over the Panel. The autohide parameters
	    can be configured in <link linkend="animtab">Global
	    Preferences dialog</link>. If you  choose to Auto Hide you
	    might want to Disable the hide buttons here as well. You
	    may also disable the hide button arrows graphics on the
	    Panel.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="panelbacktab">
    <title>Background Tab</title> <!--      <indexterm id="idx-a65">
 <primary>Panel</primary> <secondary>Background</secondary>
 </indexterm> -->
  
      <figure>
	<title>Panel Background Properties Dialog</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Panel Background Properties Dialog</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="./figures/panel_props_back"
	       format="png" srccredit="muet">
	  </graphic>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>


      <para>
	These options allow you to change the background of the Panel
       itself. You may choose, if you wish, to have the
       <guilabel>Standard</guilabel>, <guilabel>Pixmap</guilabel>, or
       <guilabel>Color</guilabel> background. The standard look for
       the Panel is determined by the GTK theme you are running at the
       time (you can configure the GTK theme using the
       <application>GNOME Control Center</application>).  The
       <guilabel>Pixmap</guilabel> option allows you to choose an
       image to tile or scale to the Panel. The
       <guilabel>Color</guilabel> option allows you to specify a
       particular color for the Panel.
      </para>

   <itemizedlist mark="bullet">

     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Color to use:</guilabel> &mdash If you choose to have
       your Panel one color, this button will launch a dialog which
       allows you to specify which color to use.
      </para>
     </listitem>


     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Image</guilabel> &mdash; If you wish to have a Pixmap
       for the background of your Panel, this section of the dialog
       allows you to choose which image to use.  If you press the
       <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button, you can search for the
       file you want to use. The current filename is shown to the left
       of this button. The window above it  shows you the preview of
       this background.
      </para>
     </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

      
      <note>
	<title>Drag and Drop With Images</title>
	<para>
	  An easier way to change the  background of your panel is to
	  drag and  drop an image  file from  the GNOME  File Manager
	  onto the Panel.  This will  automatically  change the
	  background of  the panel to that image.
	</para>
      </note>
    
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Don't scale image to fit</guilabel> &mdash; If this
       button is checked, the background image will be tiled to cover
       the panel, rather than scaled.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Scale image (keep proportions)</guilabel> &mdash; If
       this button is checked, the background image will be scaled as
       much as possible preserving image's proportions, and then the
       scaled image will be used to tile the panel.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Stretch image (change proportions)</guilabel> &mdash;
       If this button is checked, the background image will be
       stretched in both dimensions to the size of the panel.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guilabel>Rotate image for vertical panel</guilabel> &mdash;
       FIXME
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
   </sect1>

<!-- ############### Current Bugs and Limitations ############### -->

<sect1 id="panelbugs">

    <title>Current bugs and limitations</title>
    <para>
      Most of the things here are not really bugs; rather, they
      describe situations when the Panel's behaviour is not what you
      would expect.  </para>  <para>  First of all: you can't place an
      ordinary file or directory on the panel. If you try to drag and
      drop a file from the File Manager window to the panel, it won't
      work, and similarly for panels. The only type of file that can
      be placed on the panel are <filename>.desktop</filename> files,
      which describe launchers; any directory dropped on the panel
      will be interpreted as a menu &mdash; that is, all the files
      other than <filename>.desktop</filename> files will be ignored.
      </para>
    <para> Editing menus other than the Main menu is rather
      confusing. <application>Menu Editor</application> at the moment
      can not be used for this, and
      <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> item of the right-click
      menu is not too helpful either - for example, it doesn't allow
      one to change menu's icon (see <xref linkend="menusconf"> for
      instructions for doing this). This will be improved in the next
      release.
    </para>

    <para> The Main menu which you get by pressing the
      <keycap>Menu</keycap> key on the keyboard does not reflect the
      preference changes you did to the <guimenu>main menu</guimenu>
      on the panel. The reason is that you can have several
      <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> buttons on different panels.
    </para>

    <para>
     The <guibutton>Screen Lock</guibutton> button does not lock the
     screen if "No Screensaver" is set in the Control Center.
    </para>

  </sect1>


<!-- ###############  Authors  ################## -->
  <sect1 id="authors">
    <title>Authors</title>
     <para>
      <application>GNOME Panel</application> was written by many GNOME
      developers; you can find a partial list in the "About" box.
      Please send all comments, suggestions, and bug reports to the
      <ulink url="http://bugs.gnome.org" type="http">GNOME bug
      tracking database</ulink>. Instructions for submitting bug
      reports can be found on-line at <ulink
      url="http://bugs.gnome.org/Reporting.html" type="http">
      http://bugs.gnome.org/Reporting.html</ulink>. If you are using
      GNOME 1.1 or later, you can also use the command
      <command>bug-buddy</command> for submitting bug reports.
      </para>
    <para>
      This manual was written by Dave
      Mason (<email>dcm@redhat.com</email>), Dan Mueth
      (<email>d-mueth@uchicago.edu</email>), and Alexander Kirillov
      (<email>kirillov@math.sunysb.edu</email>). Please send all comments
      and suggestions regarding the manual to the GNOME Documentation
      Project at <email>docs@gnome.org</email> or enter your comments
      online using the <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.gnome.org/gdp/doctable">  GNOME Documentation
      Status Table</ulink>.
      </para>
    </sect1>


 </article>






